Finding Aid for the Collection of Sheet Music, circa 1790-1950
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Collection of Sheet Music, circa 1790-1950
Mus. Arc. 47
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
2 linear feet ( 2 boxes, 92 items )
Collection of 92 pieces of sheet music, chiefly from the United States, most with title page illustrations.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
Collection compiled by the Music Library from a combination of purchases and gifts.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains 92 pieces of sheet music, 77 of which were published in the United States, 13 in England, and 1 each in Ireland and France. The musical content is split almost evenly between piano music and vocal music with piano accompaniment. The piano music includes works in dance forms, including galops, waltzes, polkas, marches, Schottisches, quadrilles, and mazurkas. The topical subjects of the music and illustrations (43 of which are in color) American Civil War battles and persons, the transatlantic cable, and celebrities of the stage.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by composer surname, followed by title.
Container List
- Badarzewska, Thekla, 1834-1861 Modlitwa dziewicy; arranged Maiden's prayer for the piano forte, 1859, 1 score (5 pages); New York (N.Y.): S. T. Gordon For piano, four hands. Arranger: Bellak, Ja's (James) Other title: Prière exaucée (Prayer granted) Although the title Prière exaucée is stated on the title page, the music matches the work titled Prière d'une vierge. Title page illustration: a woman kneeling in prayer / printed by P. S. Duval and Son. (Box 1, Item 01)
- Baker, Thomas, active 19th century Black crook. Transformation polka; arranged Transformation polka, 1867, 1 score (8 pages); New York (N.Y.): Wm. A. Pond and Co. For piano. Other title: Black crook Dedicated to Mrs. R. D. Holmes. Color title page illustration: portrait of ballerina Mdlle. Bonfanti / lithographed by Major and Knapp Eng. Mf'g. and Lith. Co. (Box 1, Item 02)
- Baker, Thomas, active 19th century Palace garden polka Palace garden polka, 1858, 1 score (5 pages); New York (N.Y.): Horace Waters For piano. Bird song parts indicated on music. Dedicated to the Lady Patrons [of the Promenade Concerts]. Color title page illustration: view of the Palace Garden, New York City, with a bandstand and fountain, and crowd of people in attendance / lithographed by Sarony, Major, and Knapp. (Box 1, Item 03)
- Balfe, M. W. (Michael William), 1808-1870 O take me to thy heart again O take me to thy heart again, between 1866-1879, 1 score (5 pages); New York (N.Y.): Beer and Schirmer For voice and piano. Lyricist: Rankin, Jessica Other title: Oh take me to thy heart again Title page illustration: various types of filigree illuminating title / lithographed by Pearson. (Box 1, Item 04)
- Becket, Thomas à, approximately 1817-approximately 1871 He was such a nice young man He was such a nice young man: a celebrated comic song, between 1832 and 1847, 1 score (6 pages); New York (N.Y.): Firth and Hall For voice and piano. Lyricist: Alldridge, R. W. Lyricist name stated as W. R. Aldridge in caption title. Title page illustration: a man apprehending another man, with onlookers in the street and in houses above / lithographed by Fleetwood. (Box 1, Item 05)
- Blewitt, J. Tarnation strange Tarnation strange, or Yankee wonders: comic song sung by Mr. Buckingham at the Royal Gardens Vauxhall, circa 1840, 1 score (7 pages); New York (N.Y.): Firth and Hall For voice and piano. Lyricist: Coleman, Henry (Lyricist) Other title: Yankee wonders Caption title: Tarnation strange, or Yankee wonders, written by the American Boz, composed by T. Blewett. Blewitt, or Blewett, is possibly a pseudonym of publisher James Hewitt rather than English composer Jonathan Blewitt. Copy trimmed, with loss of information. Title page illustration: five comic scenes with lyrics beneath them depicting various situations described in the lyrics. (Box 1, Item 06)
- Blumenthal, Jacques Fleurs emblématiques. Pensée Pensée, no. 2 des fleurs emblématiques pour le piano, between 1858-1860, 1 score (5 pages); London (England): Cramer, Beale and Co. For piano. Other title: Fleurs emblématiques Dedicated to Miss Marshall. Full publication statement: Londres: Cramer, Beale & Co.; Paris: Brandus & Co.; Philadelphia: G. André & Co. Color title page illustration: wreath of flowers around title text. (Box 1, Item 07)
- Boieldieu, Adrien, 1775-1834 Dame blanche. Chantez joyeux menestrels. Vocal score. English Robin Adair as sung by Theodore Habelmann in the opera of La dame Blanche, 1866, 1 score (5 pages); Philadelphia (Pa.): G. Andre and Co. For voice and piano. "Correct edition as sung by Mr. Habelmann"--Caption. Title page illustration: a man playing a lute on a street to a woman above looking out from a window. (Box 1, Item 08)
- Braham, David, 1838-1905 Mulligan guard; arranged Mulligan guard, 1873, 1 score (5 pages); New York (N.Y.): Wm. A. Pond and Co. For piano. Arranger: Angelo, D. Drum and fife parts indicated on music. Dedicated to Mr. Josh Hart. Composed, arranged and performed with great success by Harrigan and Hart. Title page illustration: Harrigan & Hart in Mulligan guard uniform, with an African American boy in background holding a sign reading "M.G.". (Box 1, Item 09)
- Brougham, John, 1810-1880 Fine ould Irish gintleman Fine ould Irish gintleman, 1845, 1 score (5 pages); Boston (Mass.): Geo. P. Reed For voice and piano. Written and sung by John Brougham and dedicated to his friend Oliver C. Wyman of Boston. Title page illustration: a man with a pipe and cane in tattered clothes / lithographed by Bufford and Co. (Box 1, Item 10)
- Brown, Francis H. (Francis Henry), 1818-1891 Early dawn polka Early dawn polka, 1853, 1 score (7 pages); New York (N.Y.): William Hall and Son For piano. Dedicated to Miss Rebecca S. Burge. Color title page illustration: rooster with snowy farm in background / lithographed and printed in color by Sarony, Major, and Knapp. (Box 1, Item 11)
- Brown, Francis H. (Francis Henry), 1818-1891 Happy family polka Happy family polka, 1851, 1 score (7 pages); New York (N.Y.): Firth, Pond and Co. For piano. Dedicated to S. P. Wardwell of Providence, R. I. Title page illustration: family sitting by a fire in the parlor / lithographed by Sarony and Major. (Box 1, Item 12)
- Brown, Francis H. (Francis Henry), 1818-1891 Ocean telegraph march Ocean telegraph march, 1858, 1 score (5 pages); New York (N.Y.): Firth, Pond and Co. For piano. Dedicated to Cyrus W. Field. Title page illustration: portrait of Cyrus W. Field surrounded by flags, ships, and an ocean telegraph line side view / lithographed by Sarony, Major, and Knapp. (Box 1, Item 13)
- Buckley, Frederick, 1833-1864 I shouldn't like to tell I shouldn't like to tell: a semi comic ballad, 1858, 1 score (5 pages); Buffalo (N.Y.): Sheppard and Cottier For voice and piano. Dedicated to Miss. Hattie Bronn. Title page illustration: filigree surrounding title / lithographed by Wakelam and Bro. (Box 1, Item 14)
- Callcott, John Wall, 1766-1821 Multiplication table Multiplication table, between 1798-1807, 1 score (3 pages); Dublin (Ireland): Gough's Piano Forte, Harp, and Music Warehouse For voice and piano. (Box 1, Item 15)
- Clarke, J. P. (James Power), 1816-1889 Queen's Hussars' polka Queen's Hussars' polka, between 1848-1858, 1 score (7 pages); London (England): Jullien and Co. For voice. Dedicated to Lieutenant Colonel Shirley and the officers of the 7th (Queen's Own) Hussars. Color title page illustration: a soldier riding on a horse / lithographed by M. and N. Hanhart. (Box 1, Item 16)
- Cook, T. J. (Thomas J.) Four bells polka Four bells polka: composed as a companion to the popular "Three bells polka", 1855, 1 score (6 pages); New York (N.Y.): S. T. Gordon For piano. Addressed to Miss Elizabeth Nelson, dedicated to Captn. Creighton, of the ship Three Bells. Title page illustration: filigree featuring bells and an enlarged four note incipit / lithographed by Sarony and Co. (Box 1, Item 17)
- Coote, Charles, Jr. Snow drift galop Snow-drift galop, 1870, 1 score (7 pages); London (England): Hopwood and Crew For piano. Color title page illustration: a sled with two occupants being pulled by a horse through the snow / lithographed by Stannard and Son. (Box 1, Item 18)
- Coote, Charles, Jr. Eclipse galop Eclipse galop, 1865, 1 score (5 pages); London (England): Hopwood and Crew For piano. Color title page illustration: red, blue, and yellow curved and ornamented title lettering / lithographed by Concanen, Lee, and Siebe. (Box 1, Item 19)
- Crosby, L. V. H., -1884 Kitty Clyde Kitty Clyde, 1853, 1 score (5 pages); Syracuse (N.Y.): T. Hough For voice and piano. Dedicated to [his] friend T. Hough. Color title page illustration: portrait of a young girl fishing on a stream with a house in the background / lithographed by Sarony and Major. (Box 1, Item 20)
- Densmore, John H. (John Hopkins), 1880-1943 Longing, dear, for you Longing, dear, for you, 1919, 1 score (5 pages) and 2 parts (1 page each); Boston (Mass.): Oliver Ditson and Co. For voice, piano, violin, and violoncello. Includes parts for violin and violoncello. The parts are not indicated in the score Color title page illustration: a woman holding a string of beads amidst a flowery grove with a column in the background / E. M. Selfridge. (Box 1, Item 21)
  Title page notes that there are available versions for "high voice in G; medium voice in F; low voice in Eb". This edition is for medium voice in F.
- Dewing, A. A. M. Pharmacy Pharmacy: age-less art still majestically marches on, 1936, 1 score (5 pages); Baltimore (Md.): J. Casper Sauer For voice and piano. Dedicated to the American Pharmaceutical Association. Title page illustration: floral filigree illuminating the name of the composer. (Box 1, Item 22)
  Title page notes "the author endeavors to portray a parallel of the two dramatic arts, - MUSIC and PHARMACY. Exemplifying an exaltation accompanying any creative effort. Despite disappointments and meager encouragement, each never-the-less still lavishly contributes a solace to posterity."
- Foster, Stephen Collins, 1826-1864 Dearer than life! Dearer than life!, 1869, 1 score (2 pages); New York (N.Y.): W. J. Demorest For voice and piano. Lyricist: Cooper, George, 1840-1927 Attributed to Foster by his friend and collaborator George Cooper, who claims they worked on this song 3 weeks before Foster's death. Title page illustration: four women in late 1800's clothing with the caption "latest style of spring walking-costumes for March, 1869". Illustration on rear cover: "Latest style of street and ball costumes for March, 1869". (Box 1, Item 23)
- Foster, Stephen Collins, 1826-1864 Give this to mother Give this to Mother: Stephen C. Foster's last musical idea, 1864, 1 score (5 pages); New York (N.Y.): P. A. Wundermann For voice and piano. From a poem by S. W. Harding. Title page illustration: battle scene depicting the text of the song / lithographed by Deutz Bros. (Box 1, Item 24)
- Foster, Stephen Collins, 1826-1864 I will be true to thee I will be true to thee, 1862, 1 score (4 pages); New York (N.Y.): Horace Waters For voice and piano. Color title page illustration: red and blue filigree in geometric pattern forming a frame around the cover page text, which is the cover for a sheet music series entitled "Foster's melodies" / lithographed by Warren. (Box 1, Item 25)
- Foster, Stephen Collins, 1826-1864 Kissing in the dark Kissing in the dark: ballad, 1863, 1 score (5 pages); New York (N.Y.): John J. Daly For voice and piano. Lyricist: Cooper, George, 1840-1927 Title page illustration: filigree illuminating title text / engraved by Quidor. (Box 1, Item 26)
- Foster, Stephen Collins, 1826-1864 Laura Lee Laura Lee: song, 1851, 1 score (5 pages); Baltimore (Md.): F. D. Benteen For voice and piano. Title page illustration: filigree illuminating title text. (Box 1, Item 27)
- Foster, Stephen Collins, 1826-1864 Merry, merry month of May; arranged Merry, merry month of May: song and chorus written and composed for Clarke's School Visitor (Philadelphia), 1862, 1 score (5 pages); Boston (Mass.): Oliver Ditson and Co. For voice, chorus, and piano. The music, in the Key of B♭, is arranged as a vocal solo with piano accompaniment and as an unaccompanied mixed quartet. The air is Foster's "The White House Chair" arranged in this setting by Foster. Title page illustration: filigree illuminating title text. (Box 1, Item 28)
- Foster, Stephen Collins, 1826-1864 Oh! Lemuel! Go down to de cotton field Oh! Lemuel! Go down to de cotton field: Ethiopian song, 1850, 1 score (5 pages); Baltimore (Md.): F. D. Benteen For voice and piano, with choral refrain. Title page notes that this piece was originally performed by the Christy Minstrels and the Campbell's Minstrels. Title page illustration: filigree illuminating title text / engraved by Webb. (Box 1, Item 29)
- Foster, Stephen Collins, 1826-1864 No one to love? Why, no one to love? Answer to No one to love, 1862, 1 score (5 pages); New York (N.Y.): S. T. Gordon For voice and piano. In response to "No one to love", by M. H. Frank. Title page illustration: filigree illuminating title text / engraved by Webb. (Box 1, Item 30)
- Foster, Stephen Collins, 1826-1864 Willie we have missed you Willie we have missed you, 1854, 1 score (6 pages); New York (N.Y.): Firth, Pond and Co. For voice and piano. At head of title: "Foster's melodies, no. 25". Title page illustration: a woman greeting a man at home with children's toys on the floor / lithographed by Sarony and Co. (Box 1, Item 31)
- Fowler, J. A., 1819-1878 Watchman's polka mazurka Watchman's polka mazurka, 1855, 1 score (6 pages); New York (N.Y.): William Hall and Son For piano. Dedicated to Henry Long Esq. Title page illustration: a watchman looks over a young child sitting on a step on a snowy night / lithographed by Sarony and Co. (Box 1, Item 32)
- Franklin, Malvin M. Miserable rag Miserable rag, 1915, 1 score (5 pages); New York (N.Y.): Waterson, Berlin and Snyder Co. For piano. Color title page illustration: three dark figures playing instruments in a tree in front of a green background / illustrated by Barbelle. (Box 1, Item 33)
- Fry, William Henry, 1813-1864 Leonora. Affection waltz; arranged Affection waltz: composed and arranged for the piano forte, 1850, 1 score (3 pages); Buffalo (N.Y.): J. Sage and Sons For piano. Title page illustration: filigree around the cover page text, which is the cover for a sheet music series entitled "J. Sage and Sons Collection of Popular and Standard Waltzes, Songs, and Quick Steps, Arranged for the Piano Forte" / lithographed by Warren. (Box 1, Item 34)
- Grantham, William, composer Who'd a thought of seeing you? Who'd a thought of seeing you? Comic song sung by Mr. Buckingham, Mr. Howell, [and] Mr. Herbert, between 1834-1858, 1 score (5 pages); London (England): T. E. Purday For voice and piano. Lyricist: Farmer, Frederick Title page illustration: two men at the counter of a pawn shop with attending clerk / lithographed by George Edward Madeley. (Box 1, Item 35)
- Grobe, Charles Battle of Port Royal Battle of Port Royal, or the Bombardment of Forts Walker and Beauregard, 1861, 1 score (9 pages); Boston (Mass.): Oliver Ditson and Co. For piano. Other title: Bombardment of Forts Walker and Beauregard Programmatic narrative of the Civil War Battle of Port Royal printed above music. Dedicated to Commodore S. F. DuPont and his brave associates. Title page illustration: ships in battle at Port Royal with small battle map in bottom left corner / lithographed by John Henry Bufford. (Box 1, Item 36)
- Handy, W. C. (William Christopher), 1873-1958 Saint Louis Blues Saint Louis Blues: the international melody; the most widely known ragtime composition, 1942, 1 score (5 pages); New York (N.Y.): Handy Brothers Music Co. For voice, ukulele in D, or piano. Ukulele tablature written above piano staves. Color title page illustration: a view of St. Louis with the sun in the background; a small portrait of composer W. C. Handy in bottom right corner. (Box 1, Item 37)
- Haywood, Harry Beautiful land of somewhere Beautiful land of somewhere, 1918, 1 score (5 pages); Cleveland (Ohio): F. Heltman For voice and piano. Lyricist: Kramer, Clyde N. Color title page illustration: a woman in a yellow dress looking out over water / illustrated by Frank R. Bill. (Box 1, Item 38)
- Helmsmüller, F. B. Parade march Parade march of the 22nd regiment N. Y. S. M. Union greys, 1862, 1 score (5 pages); Boston (Mass.): Oliver Ditson and Co. For piano. Inscribed to the Officers and Members of the 22d. Regt. Title page illustration: three members of the 22nd Regiment from the Civil War, one sitting, one standing and pointing, and one looking through a spyglass. (Box 1, Item 39)
- Herbert, Victor, 1859-1924 Mlle. Modiste. If I were on the stage; arranged Kiss me again, 1915, 1 score (4 pages); New York (N.Y.): M. Witmark and Sons For voice and piano. Lyricist: Blossom, Henry, 1866-1919 Written on the theme of "If I were on the stage" from the comic opera Mlle. Modiste. Originally sung by Miss Fritzi Scheff. Title page illustration: filigree illuminating title text. (Box 1, Item 40)
- Herman, John L. (Composer) Hop-a-long one step and turkey trot Hop-a-long one step and turkey trot, 1913, 1 score (4 pages); New York (N.Y.): Jos. W. Stern and Co. For piano. Dedicated to the Sororities of the Schools of St. Louis. Color title page illustration: woman in red dress and man in tuxedo dancing together in front of a red and blue checkered background. (Box 1, Item 41)
- Herz, Jacques, 1794-1880 Cellarius valse Cellarius valse for the pianoforte, between 1853-1861, 1 score (4 pages); London (England): Cramer, Beale and Co. For piano. Dedicated to Mrs. Torre of Leamington. Color title page illustration: frame with filigree and geometric patterns around title text / illustrated by E. Bauer and printed by C. Graf. (Box 1, Item 42)
- Hess, Clifford Bric-a-brac Bric-a-brac: a novelty fox trot, 1915, 1 score (5 pages); New York (N.Y.): Waterson, Berlin and Snyder Co. For piano. Color title page illustration: anthropomorphized housewares walking amongst each other. (Box 1, Item 43)
- Himmel, Friedrich Heinrich, 1765-1814 Gebet während der Schlacht. English Battle prayer, circa 1845, 1 score (6 pages); Boston (Mass.): E. H. Wade For voice and piano. Lyricist: Besant, Walter, 1836-1901 Words by Walter Maurice. Color title page illustration: a knight kneeling in prayer and looking upward / lithographed by W. Sharp. (Box 1, Item 44)
- Hobson, M. (Martin) Somebody Somebody: semi comic song, 1859, 1 score (5 pages); Buffalo (N.Y.): Blodgett and Bradford For voice and piano. Lyricist: Gildersleeve, C. H., Mrs. Addressed to Miss Ellen Hart, Buffalo. Title page illustration: filigree illuminating the title text along with a small woman drawn in the letter "S" of "Somebody". (Box 1, Item 45)
- Hook, Mr. (James), 1746-1827 Dear is my little native vale Dear is my little native vale, circa 1790, 1 score (3 pages); London (England): Preston and Son For voice and orchestra. Condensed score with flute, horn, and additional violin parts indicated on music. "Sung by Miss Milne at Vauxhall". (Box 1, Item 46)
- Hook, Mr. (James), 1746-1827 Sweet lillies of the valley Sweet lillies of the valley: a favorite song, 1793?, 1 score (3 pages); London (England): Longman and Broderip For voice, two violins, and continuo (unfigured bass). Lyricist: Richardson, Mr., active 18th century Condensed score on three staves; with a version for the guitar. "Sung with universal applause at Vauxhall Gardens by Master Shepherd". (Box 1, Item 47)
- Hunt, G. W. (George W.), approximately 1839-1904 That's where you make the mistake That's where you make the mistake, 1869, 1 score (5 pages); London (England): Hopwood and Crew For voice and piano. Arranger: Hobson, M. (Martin) Other title: That's where you make a mistake Color title page illustration: portrait of George Leybourne, original singer of the piece / lithographed by Alfred Concanen. (Box 1, Item 48)
- Kaye, Buddy Penny a kiss, a penny a hug Penny a kiss - a penny a hug, 1950, 1 score (3 pages); New York (N.Y.): Shapiro, Bernstein and Co. For voice and piano (or ukelele). Ukulele tablature written above piano staves. Color title page illustration: a man and woman hugging while the woman places a penny in a jar, along with a portrait of Eddy Howard. (Box 2, Item 49)
- Kern, Jerome, 1885-1945 Show boat. Ol' man river. Vocal score Ol' man river [from] Show boat: adapted from Edna Ferber's novel of the same name, 1927, 1 score (7 pages); New York (N.Y.): T. B. Harms Company For voice and piano (or ukelele). Lyricist: Hammerstein, Oscar, II, 1895-1960 Other title: Show boat Ukulele tablature written above piano staves. Title notes that this piece is an excerpt from a Florence Ziegfeld presentation. Color title page illustration: women and men in fancy dress boarding a boat / lithographed by Doubleday, Page, and Co. (Box 2, Item 50)
- Ketèlbey, Albert W. (Albert William), 1875-1959 Tangled tunes Tangled tunes: a pot-pourri of 106 favourite melodies humorously entangled, 1915, 1918, 1 score (17 pages) and 1 part (9 pages); London (England): Ascherberg, Hopwood and Crew For piano or orchestra. Other title: Tangled tunes. Selection of 106 favourite melodies Part is for violin/conductor. Color title page illustration: a man in a red cape standing over a cauldron with smoke containing titles of some included song selections / lithographed by W. George. (Box 2, Item 51)
  First page of 1st violin score notes "this selection is so arranged that it can be played in two parts, with finish (adlib) at Page 5. The Conductor should instruct the Orchestra before-hand to omit the six bars before 'Lass of Richmond Hill' (19 bars before letter G) if the whole Selection is to be played without break. It is essential for the success of this selection that the tempo should not be changed from tune to tune, but that each melody should run into the next as nearly L'istesso tempo as possible - otherwise the musical joke is lost. Columbia Records of this Selection, Conducted by A. W. Ketèlbey may be obtained".
- Kinkel, Charles Strawberries and cream march Strawberries and cream: march, 1868, 1 score (9 pages); New York (N.Y.): J. L. Peters For piano. Dedicated to Miss Ella Lutkins. Color title page illustration: a bowl of strawberries and cream on a patterned tablecloth / lithographed by Ehrgott, Forbriger and Co. (Box 2, Item 52)
- Kleber, H. (Henry), 1816-1897 Atlantic telegraph schottisch Atlantic telegraph schottisch, 1857, 1 score (5 pages); New York (N.Y.): Firth, Pond and Co. For piano. 2nd edition. Title page illustration: the USS Niagara and SS Agamemnon in the water off Newfoundland completing the transatlantic cable, with onlookers on land / lithographed by Sarony, Major and Knapp. (Box 2, Item 53)
- Kleber, H. (Henry), 1816-1897 Rainbow schottisch Rainbow schottisch, 1852, 1 score (5 pages); New York (N.Y.): Firth, Pond and Co. For piano. Color title page illustration: a grassy path on the water lined with trees with a rainbow in the background / lithographed by Sarony and Major. (Box 2, Item 54)
- Kleber, Henry, 1816-1897 Rainbow schottisch Rainbow schottisch, 1864, 1 score (5 pages); Boston (Mass.): Oliver Ditson and Co. For piano. 120th edition. Color title page illustration: a man and two women viewing a rainbow / lithographed by N.E. Lith. Steam. (Box 2, Item 55)